Inventory of the Virginia Cole Trenholm Papers, 1929-1979
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Virginia Cole Trenholm papers
1929-1979
Trenholm, Virginia Cole, 1902-
03597
2.25 cubic feet (5 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Biography of Virginia Cole Trenholm
Virginia Cole Trenholm (1902-1994) was a historian who wrote four books on the Shoshoni and Arapaho Indians of the Wind River Reservation in Wyoming.
Scope and Content
Collection includes correspondence (1929-1979); subject files containing correspondence, research notes, etc. (1929-1974); newspaper clippings; and research notebooks which contain correspondence, contracts with publishers, etc.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Virginia Cole Trenholm at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The collection was received from Virginia Cole Trenholm in 1980.
Access Terms
Authors, American.; Indians of North America -- Wyoming.; Women historians.; Shoshoni Indians.; Arapaho Indians.; Wind River Indian Reservation (Wyo.); Wyoming -- History -- 1890-1918.; Wyoming -- History -- 1919-1945.; Wyoming -- History -- 1946-;; Historians.
People, Ethnicity, and Culture; Native Americans; Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Social Life and Customs; Wyoming
Container List
- Articles:
  - "Frank Huston and His Comments", THE CUSTER MYTH, by Col. W. A. Graham. Xerox copy with annotation in red and black ink (Box 1)
  - "Another Version of the Story of 'Red Horse,' "THE CUSTER MYTH, by Col W. A. Graham. Xerox copy with annotation in red and black ink (Box 1)
  - "The Arikara", THE CUSTER MYTH, by Col. W. A. Graham. Xerox copy with annotation in red and black ink (Box 1)
  - "The Great Significance of Indian Names", EMPIRE MAGAZINE, by Opal Hartsell Brown. Xerox copy; original returned to donor (Box 1)
  - "Indians", Xerox copy (Box 1)
  - "Indians of Wyoming", LEAGUE OF WOMEN VOTERS PUBLICATION # 35. Xerox copy (Box 1)
  - "Photographic Collections of the Bureau of American Ethnology", SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION, BUREAU OF AMERICAN ETHNOLOGY (Box 1)
  - "Robert Foote", ANNALS OF WYOMING, by Mrs. Charles Ellis. Xerox copy (Box 1)
  - "Swan Company Memories 1925 to 1939", by Robert R. Larson. Note to Virginia, from Robert, attached, April 30, 1980 (Box 1)
  - "Photographic Collections of the Bureau of American Ethnology", SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION, BUREAU OF AMERICAN ETHNOLOGY (Box 1)
- Booklets:
  - ABOUT ARIZONA. The Valley National Bank, 1967 (Box 1)
  - ALL AMERICAN INDIAN DAYS. Sheridan Wyoming. August 4, 5, 6, 1967 (Box 1)
  - ALL AMERICAN DAYS. Sheridan, Wyoming, 1973 (Box 1)
  - AMERICAN INDIANS AND THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT. United States Department of the Interior, Bureau of Indian Affairs (Box 1)
  - THE AMERICAN INDIANS: ANSWERS TO 101 QUESTIONS. United States Department of the Interior of Indian Affairs (Box 1)
  - ANSWERS TO YOUR QUESTIONS ABOUT AMERICAN INDIANS. United States Department of the Interior, Bureaus of Indian Affairs, 1970 (Box 1)
  - BENT'S FORT ON THE ARKANSAS. State Historical Society of Colorado, 1954 (Box 1)
  - THE CHEROKEES PAST AND PRESENT. J. Ed. Sharpe, Cherokee Publications, 1970 (Box 1)
  - COLORADO'S HALL OF FAME. Mary and Gene Martin, Little London Press, 1974 (Box 1)
  - DE GRAZIA PAINTS THE YAQUI. Ted De Grazia, University of Arizona Press, 1968 (Box 1)
  - THE FIVE CIVILIZED TRIBES. Grant Foreman, Hoffman Printing Company, 1966 (Box 1)
  - FORT FETTERMAN'S CEMETERY. Sharon Lass Field, 1970 (Box 1)
  - FORT GIBSON. Grant Foreman, Hoffman-Speed Printing Co. (Box 1)
  - FORT VASQUEZ. Leroy R. Hafen, The State Historical Society of Colorado, 1964 (Box 1)
  - A GUIDE FOR VISITORS TO THE WINSTON CHURCHILL MEMORIAL AND LIBRARY IN THE UNITED STATES. Westminster College/Fulton/Missouri (Box 1)
  - HANDBOOK FOR BEGINNING NEWSPAPER SPONSORS. Joe W. Milner, and Louise Flynn, 1966 (Box 1)
  - INDIAN BROTHER BUFFALO. Lena Lockhart Daugherty and Gladys Wheeler Jeffords, 1971 (Box 1)
  - INDIANS OF THE CENTRAL PLAINS. United States Department of the Interior, Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1966 (Box 1)
  - INDIANS OF THE NORTHWEST. United States Department of the Interior, Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1968 (Box 1)
  - AN INTRODUCTION TO THE MUSEUM. Joslyn Art Museum, Omaha, Nebraska, 1968 (Box 1)
  - MISSION CHURCH AND GROUNDS. The National Park Service, 1967 (Box 1)
  - MISSOURI: VACATION GUIDE. Missouri Tourism Commission (Box 1)
  - OKLAHOMA'S FABULOUS INDIAN NAMES. Gladys Wheeler Jeffords and Lena Lockhart Daughtery, American Printing Company, 1962 (Box 1)
  - THE PIONEERS CAME. Ray Morissette, 1967 (Box 1)
  - SECOND ANNUAL REPORT ON A CONFERENCE ON INDIAN EDUCATION. Fremont County School Administrators, 1969 (Box 1)
  - SURGEON'S DIARY WITH THE CUSTER RELIEF COLUMN. W. Boyes, WJBM Associates, 1974 (Box 1)
  - THE TRAIL OF TEARS HISTORIC DRAMA 1974. The Theatre at Tsa-La-Gi (Box 1)
  - VACATIONING WITH INDIANS. U.S. Department of the Interior, Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1965 (Box 1)
  - WYOMING COMMUNITY COLLEGES (Box 1)
  - WYOMING'S SECOND EQUALITY CONGRESS. The First Women's Congress in Wyoming, 1975 (Box 1)
- Books:
  - CROSSROADS OF THE WEST. Crossroads of the West, Inc., 1965 (Box 1)
  - THE FORTS OF OKLAHOMA. Vinson Lackey, Tulsa Printing Company, 1963 (Box 1)
  - GUIDE TO WYOMING NEWSPAPERS 1867-1967. Lola Homsher, Wyoming State Library, 1971 (Box 1)
  - HIGH COUNTRY NAMES. Louisa Ward Arps and Elinor Eppich Kingery, The Colorado Mountain Club, 1966 (Box 1)
  - TWENTIETH CENTURY PIONEERING. Mary J. Allyn, Privately Printed by Author, 1956 (Box 1)
  - WORKBOOK FOR WYOMING PAGEANT. Maurine Carley and Virginia Cole Trenholm, Bailey School Supply Casper, Wyoming, 1959 (Box 1)
- Correspondence:
  - 3 Blank Postcards (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Kathy Tuggle, undated (Box 2)
  - TO: Virginia FROM: Charlotte Smith, undated (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Karen Merklin and Mrs. Kallal's 5th period class, undated (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: 7th period class, undated (Box 2)
  - TO: Virginia Cole Trenholm FROM: Cliff, undated (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Cindy Layman, Class Secretary, 2nd period, February 14, no year (Box 2)
  - TO: Mr. Robert Standing Water FROM: Mrs. Virginia C. Trenholm, November 14, 1966 (Box 2)
  - TO: Miss Virginia Cole Trenholm FROM: Ada P. Kahn, April 13, 1967 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Virginia Cole Trenholm FROM: Ada P. Kahn, May 22, 1967 (Box 2)
  - TO: Virginia FROM: Edward A. Shaw, October 29, 1968 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Virginia Trenholm FROM: Gordon Ward, November 14, 1968 (Box 2)
  - TO: Virginia FROM: Ardeline Spotted Elk, September 1970 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Virginia Trenholm FROM: Laramie County Chapter Wyoming State Historical Society, October 1971 (Box 2)
  - TO: Susan Scott FROM: Virginia Cole Trenholm, November 23, 1971 (Box 2)
  - TO: Virginia Trenholm FROM: Mrs. Judy Kallal, December 1, 1971 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Virginia Trenholm FROM: Rella Looney, December 3, 1971 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Virginia Trenholm FROM: Mrs. Judy Kallal, December 6, 1971 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Maurice, December 13, 1971 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Virginia Cole Trenholm FROM: Mrs. Stan Hathaway, February 2, 1972 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Mrs. Kallal's 6th period class, February 16, 1972 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Debbie Albert, class secretary, period 3, February 16, 1972 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Debbie Albert, class secretary, period 3, February 17, 1972 (Box 2)
  - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Stan Scheer, March 20, 1972 (Box 2)
  - TO: Virginia FROM: T. A. Larson, April 7, 1972 (Box 2)
  - TO: Ms. Virginia Cole Trenholm FROM: W. Boyes, March 28, 1975 (Box 2)
- Folders:
  - ARAPAHOES:
    - Articles:
      - "Among the Arapahoes" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Arapahoes" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "The Arapahoe Indians" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Arapahoe Indian is Distinguished Churchman" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Arapahoe Ranch Operating Agreement" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "The Arapahoe Padlock Ranch" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "A Bed For God" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "C. & A. Agency" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Centennial Vesper Service" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Cheyennes" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Cheyennes and Arapahoes in Colorado to 1861" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Chief Left Hand's Life" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Chiefs" (has manuscript notes) (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Journal of the West, The Arapahoes, Our People" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "The Legend of Castle Gardens" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "The Northern Arapaho Flat Pipe and the Ceremony of Covering in the Pipe" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Procedures of a Council of Cheyenne and Arapahoe Indians" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "The Puzzle of Sand Creek" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Sand Creek" (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - "Some Background on the Cheyenne and Arapahoe Indians" (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Booklets:
      - Northern Arapahoe, Robert Hand (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Questions and Answers in Arapahoe, Fremont Arthur (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - A Thumbnail History of Holy Trinity Church: Kirkdale Through The Ages, Alleda Nixon (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Book: THE HISTORY OF EATON, COLORADO, Pauline Allison (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence:
      - TO: Mr. Campbell FROM: Truman Michelson, February 19, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - TO: Mr. W. S. Campbell FROM: Bird Grinnell, May 6, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - TO: Stanley Vestal FROM: Dorothy Gardener, November 18, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Paul Vance, March 17, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - TO: Willie Hall FROM: William H. Payne, November 8, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Lawrence C. Parnell, April 7, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Jack D. Haley, October 21, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Rella Looney, March 28, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings (18) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Newspapers:
      - "Empire" (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - "The Riverton Ranger" (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - "Wyoming State Journal" (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Pamphlets:
      - Big Mountain Country Wyoming (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - University of Oklahoma Press (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Big Wyoming (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Information on Reservation (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - List of Arapahoe Names (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - List of Source Materials for Indian Books (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ARTICLES:
    - Articles:
      - "About the Author" (Box 2)
      - "Big Smoke" (Box 2)
      - "Fact or Fiction: Which Whall it be?" (Box 2)
      - "Fringe Benefits of Writing" (2) (Box 2)
      - "The Indian Role in Fort Laramie History" (Box 2)
      - "The Shoshone Role in Western History" (Box 2)
      - "The Shoshone Woman and Her Status in the Tribe" (Box 2)
      - "The Shoshonis of Wyoming" (Box 2)
      - "The Wind River Indians" (Box 2)
      - No Title (Box 2)
    - Booklets:
      - Annals of Wyoming, The Wyoming State Archives, 1954 (Box 2)
      - Glendo Dam Dedication, 1959 (Box 2)
      - Wheatland's First Church, Virginia Cole Trenholm, 1957 (Box 2)
      - The Wind River Rendezvous, St. Stephens Indian Mission (Box 2)
      - Wyoming Stream Names, Dee Linford, Wyoming Game and Fish Department, 1944 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence:
      - TO: Mrs. Virginia Trenholm FROM: Robert H. Burns, Apr. 5, 19?? (Box 2)
      - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: R. E. McWhinnie, Apr. 26, 19?? (Box 2)
      - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: David A. Wolff, Mar. 13, 19?? (Box 2)
      - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Dave Wolff, Apr. 24, 19?? (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings (7) (Box 2)
    - Periodicals:
      - Montana Western History, Volume XII, No. 4, Autumn 1962 (Box 2)
      - True West, February 1962 (Box 2)
      - True West, February 1963 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Notecards for "Shoshone Role in Western History" (Box 2)
      - Notes for "History of the Indian Tribes of the U.S. (Box 2)
      - Outline for "The Making of a Book" (Box 2)
      - Pamphlet: Glendo, Wyoming Advertising (Box 2)
      - Questions concerning Indians and Pilgrims (Box 2)
      - Questions from the students of HST 202 (Box 2)
      - Warfare in Indian Pains Culture (Box 2)
  - AMANDA MARY:
    - Articles:
      - "History of Natrona County" (Box 2)
      - "In the Court of Claims of the United States" (4) (Box 2)
      - "Welcome and History of Arlington" (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings (5) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Booklet - "Amanda Mary and the Dog Soldiers", Virginia Cole Trenholm, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence - TO: Ms. Trenholm FROM: Sandra E. Guzzo, August 23, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Excerpts from "The Colorado Magazine" and "Wyoming, Tour 2" (Box 2)
      - Information form "Wyoming Library Roundup" (Box 2)
      - Newspaper - "The Riverton Ranger" (Box 2)
      - Sheet of paper containing information about "Amanda Mary and the Dog Soldiers" (Box 2)
  - BLUE BOOK:
    - Articles:
      - "Building A State Government" (2) (Box 3)
      - "Wyoming Blue Book" (Box 3)
      - No Title (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings (18) (Box 3)
    - Periodicals:
      - Wyoming History News, Vol. 21, No. 5, September 1974 (Box 3)
      - By-Lines of Wyoming Press Women, September 1974 (Box 3)
    - Press Releases (3) (Box 3)
    - Style Sheets (2) (Box 3)
  - INDIANS (MISCELLANEOUS):
    - Articles:
      - "Chronicler of Cowboys and Indians" (Box 3)
      - "Indians of Wyoming" (Box 3)
      - "The Slaughter" (Box 3)
      - "Some Fringe Benefits of Authorship" (Box 3)
      - "Twenty Years of Peyote Studies" (Box 3)
      - "Welcome to Zuni" (Box 3)
      - "The Wind River Rendezvous, The Legend of Castle Gardens" (Box 3)
    - Booklets:
      - "The Emergence of the Plains Indian as the Symbol of the North American Indian", John C. Ewers, Smithsonian Institution, 1965 (Box 3)
      - "Folk Art in the Fur Trade of the Upper Missouri", John C. Ewers, Journal of the National Archives, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Maps: (Box 3)
      - Arapaho Migrations (Box 3)
      - Indian Country Legend (Box 3)
      - Indian Tribes and Linguistic Stocks, 1650 (Box 3)
      - No Title (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings (9) (Box 3)
    - Newspapers:
      - "Empire" (Box 3)
      - "Wind River Press" (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Bibliography - Indians of Wyoming (Box 3)
      - Correspondence - TO: Mrs. Trenholm FROM: Alexander Bordeaux Jr., May 10, 1953 (Box 3)
      - List of Books About Indians Who Have Lived in Wyoming (Box 3)
      - Suggested Reading List - Arapahoe (Box 3)
      - Suggested Reading List - Shoshone and Bannock (Box 3)
  - MAYFLOWER:
    - Articles:
      - "Indians and Pilgrims" (Box 3)
      - "The Mayflower Compact" (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings (4) (Box 3)
  - PLATTE COUNTY:
    - Articles: (Box 3)
      - "An Evening With Ruth Frederick" (Box 3)
      - "Platte County's Historical Background" (Box 3)
      - "The Wyoming Development Company" (Box 3)
    - Correspondence - TO: Mrs. Ruth H. Baker FROM: Gene M. Gressley, Jan. 21, 19?? (Box 3)
    - Correspondence - TO: Executive Secretary FROM: Mary E. Anders, Mar. 20, 19?? (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings (2) (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Inventory of the County Archives of Wyoming (Box 3)
      - The Midwest Review (xerox), October 1925 (Box 3)
      - "My Cowboy Days" (Box 3)
      - Pamphlet - Glendo, Wyoming Advertising (Box 3)
      - Receipt (Box 3)
      - "Wyoming Cowboy Days" (Box 3)
  - SHOSHONES:
    - Articles:
      - "Meet a Shoshoni Who's Also in the Mayflower Society" (Box 3)
      - "The Red Blooded All American Sound" (Box 3)
      - "Sheridan Renews Indian Days" (Box 3)
      - "The Shoshone: The Tribe of the Great Basin" (Box 3)
      - "Shoshoni: A Mini Grammar" (Box 3)
      - "Shoshonis: Sentinels of the Rockies" (2) (Box 3)
      - "The Shoshoni Sister" (Box 3)
      - "Thumbnail History of the Shoshone-Bannock Indians" (2) (Box 3)
      - "Wind River Indian Reservation: Resume" (Box 3)
      - "Wind River Reservation, Wyoming: Self-Guided Tour" (Box 3)
      - No Title (Box 3)
    - Booklets:
      - Days of Old Fort Hall: Indian Celebration, Fort Hall Indian Reservation, July, 1952 (Box 3)
      - Gift of the Waters, Mary Montabe (Box 3)
      - Life of Chief Washakie and Shoshone Indians, H. D. Del Monte, Deseret News Press, 1964 (Box 3)
      - The Question of Bannock Territory, Omar C. Stewart (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings (9) (Box 3)
    - Newspapers:
      - "Pioneer Ed." (Box 3)
      - "The Wyoming Churchman" (Box 3)
      - "Wyoming State Journal" (3) (Box 3)
      - "Wyoming State Tribune and Wyoming Eagle" (Box 3)
    - Pamphlets:
      - Noble Hotel, Lander, Wyoming (Box 3)
      - The Missionary District of Wyoming (Box 3)
      - Shoshone: Arts and Crafts (Box 3)
    - Periodicals:
      - Bits and Pieces, Volume 4, Number 4, April 1968 (Box 3)
      - Playgrounds of the Rockies, May 1963 (Box 3)
    - S Miscellaneous:
      - Correspondence - TO: Author and Friend FROM: Savoie Lottinville, June 10, 1967 (Box 3)
      - Interpretation of Indian Hieroglyphics (Box 3)
      - Notes from a letter to Nellie Scott (Box 3)
      - "Summer in Wyoming", magazine cover (Box 3)
  - UTES:
    - Articles: "Facts About Unitah & Ouray Agency and Indian Reservation" (Box 3)
    - Booklets: The Utes Are People With Ideas (Box 3)
    - Newspapers:
      - "Uintah Basin Travel & Recreation" (2 issues) (Box 3)
      - "The Ute Bulletin" (2 issues) (Box 3)
    - Pamphlets:
      - Big U Country (Box 3)
      - Bottle Hollow Resort & Convention Center (Box 3)
      - Buffalo Run's Bottle Hollow (Box 3)
      - Buffalo Run: Utah's Only Dude Resort (2) (Box 3)
      - Dagget County: Home of Flaming Gorge (Box 3)
      - Dinosaur Gardens (Box 3)
      - Dinosaurland, Northeastern Utah (2) (Box 3)
      - Discover Dinosaurland, Daggett, Duchesne (Box 3)
      - Jolly Roger (Box 3)
      - Jolly Roger Restaurant (Box 3)
      - The State Parks of Utah (Box 3)
      - Utah! National Park State (Box 3)
      - Utah Story (Box 3)
    - Postcards (2) (Box 3)
  - WEST OF PLYMOUTH:
    - Articles: "Trenholm Honored In Platte County Programs" (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings (7) (Box 3)
  - WIND RIVER RESERVATION:
    - Articles:
      - "Arapahoe Ranch Operating Agreement" (Box 3)
      - "Wind River Reservation Resume as of December, 1976" (Box 3)
      - "Wind River Reservation Resume, Location" (Box 3)
      - "Wyoming Citizens for Equality in Government" (Box 3)
    - Booklets:
      - Fishing Regulations, Office of the Fish and Game Department, 1973 (Box 3)
      - The Wind River Reservation: Yesterday and Today (Box 3)
    - Maps:
      - Reservation (Box 3)
      - Indian Country (3) (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings (27) (Box 3)
    - Pamphlets:
      - Arapahoe Cultural Museum (Box 3)
      - Big Wyoming, Wind River Reservation (2) (Box 3)
      - Community Profile: Ft. Washakie, Wyoming. (Box 3)
      - St. Micheal's Mission, Ethete (Box 3)
      - Take a Look at the Wind River Reservation (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Correspondence - TO: Virginia Trenholm FROM: The family of Chuck McAdams, undated (Box 3)
      - Notes Taken Entirely from The Wind River Reservation - Yesterday and Today (Box 3)
  - WYOMING:
    - Articles:
      - "In the Supreme Court, State of Wyoming" (Box 3)
      - "Mama's Gone to Sit on the Jury" (Box 3)
      - "Wyoming Celebrates Her Admission Into The Union" (Box 3)
    - Booklets: "Wyoming, Some Historical Facts", Wyoming State Archives and Historical Department, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Map Keys:
      - Central Wyoming Brochure (Box 3)
      - Northern Wyoming Brochure (Box 3)
      - Southern Wyoming Brochure (Box 3)
      - Western Wyoming Brochure (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings (2) (Box 3)
    - Newspapers:
      - "Daily Sun" (Box 3)
      - "Freeman Report" (Box 3)
    - Periodicals: National Geographic, Volume 129, No. 4, April 1966 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - Correspondence - TO: John W. Meldrum (telegram) FROM: J. M. Caren (xerox), July 10, 1890 (Box 3)
      - Program for The Equal Rights Amendment Coalition (Box 3)
      - Announcement (Box 3)
- NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS:
  - Arapahoe Clippings (64) (Box 4)
  - Shonshone Clippings (39) (Box 4)
  - Extra Clippings (31) (Box 4)
- NEWSPAPERS:
  - "Arizona" from The Arizona Republic, 5 pages, March 3, 1968 (Box 4)
  - "Arizona" from The Arizona Republic, 10 pages, January 7, 1968 (Box 4)
  - "Education Section" from The Christian Science Monitor, 8 pages, November 10, 1975 (Box 4)
  - "Empire" from The Denver Post, 6 pages, September 14, 1975 (Box 4)
- NOTEBOOKS:
  - Blue Notebook: Contains pictures, clippings, correspondence, articles, publisher contracts, instructions on manuscript writings and proof reading; all concerning books written by Virginia Trenholm (Box 4)
  - Blue Notebook: Contains articles, clippings, and pictures concerning books written by Virginia Trenholm (Box 4)
  - Light Blue Notebook: Contains clippings, programs, correspondence, photographs, booklets, news letters, all concerning different aspects of Indians (Box 5)
  - Blue Folder: "Nez Perce", articles and pictures of the Nez Perce, "Idaho's Indians"; also included, a clipping entitled "The Indian Renaissance" (Box 5)
  - Plastic Folder: "The Old Depot", clippings from magazines pasted on purple paper. Also included, a magazine article, "The Trials of the Iron Horse" (Box 5)
  - Red Folder: "Bob Warner", article 'Fort Laramie or Sublettes Fort, Near the Nebraska or Platte River' (Box 5)
- PAMPHLETS:
  - All American Indian Days. Sheridan, Wyoming, August 4-6, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Black Hills Passion Play. Spearfish, South Dakota, June 3, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Black Hills of South Dakota. Sturgis, South Dakota (Box 5)
  - Devils Tower. National Park Service, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Grand Tetons. Jackson, Wyoming, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Grand Tetons. Jackson, Wyoming, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Missouri's Executive Mansion. Jefferson City, Missouri (Box 5)
  - Native American Arts. National Park Service, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Oklahoma Tours. Tulsa, Oklahoma (Box 5)
  - Old Fort Gibson. Muskogee, Oklahoma, August 23-24, 1975 (Box 5)
  - The Passion Play. Black Hills (Box 5)
  - Teton Village. Jackson Hole, Wyoming, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Tsa-La-Gi Inn. Tahlequah, Oklahoma (Box 5)
  - Tsa-La-Gi. Cherokee National Historical Society, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Tsa-La-Gi. Cherokee National Historical Society (Box 5)
  - Union Pacific. May 9, 1980 (Box 5)
- PERIODICALS:
  - "The American West". Volume XVI, Number 3, May/June 1979 (Box 5)
  - "Arizona Highway". A Treasury, 1967 (Box 5)
  - "Arizona Highway", March 1975 (Box 5)
  - "The Conservationist", January-February 1976 (Box 5)
  - "The Delta Kappa Gamma Bulletin". Volume XLII Number 1, Fall 1975 (Box 5)
  - "Deskbook of the School of Journalism". Series 138, 1956 (Box 5)
  - "The Indian", September 22, 1968 (Box 5)
  - "Oklahoma Today". Volume 24, Number 4. 5 pages, Autumn 1974 (Box 5)
  - "Wyoming", 1975 (Box 5)
  - "The Denver Post". "The Red Man's Last Struggle", 1966 (Box 5)
- PHOTOGRAPHS:
  - Arapaho:
    - Alexander, Jr., grandson of James Bordeaux. This picture was taken in his youth (PHOTO (B-B644-L))
    - Andrew Brazil standing beside his father's grave. The Reverend John R. Robert's beside. The Wind River Sacagawea Indian Mission in backgroun. (PHOTO (B-Sa14))
    - Arapaho Indians Smoking [Sketched by Theodore R. Davis, Harper's Weekly, June 29, 1967] (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
    - Buffalo Meat, an Arapaho, follows the white man's road, while his two Cheyenne allies relax in Indian attire. Cheyenne and Arapaho Indians at Ben Beveridge's boarding house on 3rd St., Washington D. C.. Left to right: Buffalo Meat, Three Fingers, and Wolf Robe (PHOTO (B-B863-m))